A Finding Aid to the James Fitzgerald Papers, 1905-1992, in the Archives of American Art AAA.fitzjame
Archives of American Art
James Fitzgerald papers
1905-1992
AAA.fitzjame
Archives of American Art
4.6 Linear feet
The papers of painter James Fitzgerald measure 4.6 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1992. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and business correspondence, including fifty-one letters from Rockwell Kent; personal business records; writings; artwork consisting of drawings and 21 sketchbooks; printed material, including a scrapbook of clippings and catalogs; and photographs of Fitzgerald, his family and friends, and his work.
Fitzgerald, James, 1899-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated in 1991 by Fitzgerald’s literary executors, Anne and Edgar Hubert. Two additional sketchbooks were donated in 2014 by the chairman of the James Fitzgerald Legacy, Robert L. Stahl.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter James Fitzgerald (1899-1971) lived and worked in Monterey, California and Monhegan, Maine and is known for his watercolors of seascapes, animals, and nature.
Born in Milton, Massachusetts, Fitzgerald studied from 1919 to 1923 at the Massachusetts School of Art and from 1923 to 1924 at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts School with Philip Hale, Leslie P. Thompson, and Edmund C. Tarbell. From 1923 to 1928, Fitzgerald took a break from his art studies to travel, sailing and crewing on fishing ships and freighters on the coasts of northern America. During a trip along the West coast in 1928, his travels brought him to Monterey, California where he established a studio and met and became associated with a group including John Cage, Martha Graham, E. F. Ricketts, and John Steinbeck.
From 1936 to 1942, Fitzgerald taught painting in California, then sold his studio the following year to settle in the artists’ colony at Monhegan, Maine, which he had first visited in 1923. From 1944 to 1971, Fitzgerald made annual trips to Mt. Katahdin and also formed friendships with other Monhegan residents, including Rockwell Kent and Anne and Edgar Hubert. Fitzgerald died suddenly on the Irish island of Arranmore Ireland, where he had traveled to paint in 1971.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter James Fitzgerald measure 4.6 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1992. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and business correspondence, including fifty-one letters from Rockwell Kent; personal business records; writings; artwork consisting of drawings and 21 sketchbooks; printed material, including a scrapbook of clippings and catalogs; and photographs of Fitzgerald, his family and friends, and his work.
Biographical materials include certificates, military records, and identification cards and passports. Correspondence is with collectors and friends, including Monhegan residents Anne and Edgar Hubert, Grace Sullivan, and Rockwell Kent. Personal business records include banking, tax, and estate records. Writings consist of Fitzgerald's notebook and notes, essays and recollections of Fitzgerald by friends, and Calvin Hennig's notes on a 1984 posthumous exhibition catalog.
There are loose drawings and 21 sketchbooks of Fitzgerald's artwork. Printed material includes clippings, a clippings scrapbook, exhibition catalogs, and a five-minute video recording describing the holdings of Anne and Edgar Hubert's Fitzgerald art collection. Photographs are of Fitzgerald, his friends and family, residents, travel snapshots, and photographs and slides of his artwork.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1918-1971 (2 folders; Boxes 1, 5)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1934-1987 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1948-1972 (0.5 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Writings, 1955-1988 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 2-3, 5)
Series 5: Artwork, 1930-1969 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 4-6)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1923-1989 (0.2 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 7: Photographic Material, 1905-1992 (0.3 linear feet; Box 4)
Hennig, Calvin; Hubert, Anne, 1909-2004; Hubert, Edgar, 1909-1994; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Art--Collectors and collecting; Artist colonies; Drawings; Marine painters--California--Monterey; Marine painters--Maine--Monhegan; Monhegan Island (Me.); Painters--California--Monterey; Painters--Maine; Painting, Modern--20th century--United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Slides (photographs); Video recordings
- Biographical Materials, 1918-1971; Series 1; 2 Folders Boxes 1, 5
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include copies of Fitzgerald's birth certificate, honorary discharge papers from the Marines, a social security card, and 2 passports from 1964 and 1971.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Certificates, 1918-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, Folder 1.
  - Identification Cards and Passports, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Certificate from Box 1, Folder 1, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1934-1987; Series 2; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters to collectors and friends, including Anne and Edgar Hubert and Grace Sullivan. Notable are fifty-one letters from Rockwell Kent primarily discussing Fitzgerald's and Kent's interests and property in Monhegan, Maine. Letters from Monhegan Associates, Inc., a group devoted to preservation of Monhegan Island, contains by-laws, minutes of meetings, and newsletters.
  With the exception of correspondence with Rockwell Kent and Monhegan Associates Inc., letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Monhegan Associates, Inc., 1958-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chronological, circa 1934-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chronological, 1934-1959 (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
  - Chronological, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 23-30)
  - Chronological, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 31-38)
  - Chronological, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39-44)
  - Chronological, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 45-54)
  - Chronological, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 55-59)
  - Chronological, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 60-63)
  - Chronological, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 64-68)
  - Chronological, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 69-73)
  - Chronological, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Chronological, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
  - Chronological, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Chronological, 1972-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Personal Business Records, 1948-1972; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include bank statements, cancelled checks, income tax and insurance records, receipts, some for gilding work and art supplies, and estate records.
  - Bank Statements, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19-23)
  - Checks, Canceled, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24-27)
  - Stocks, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Tax, Income, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Tax, Miscellaneous, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Veterans Administration and Retirement, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Insurance, 1956-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Receipts, Medical, 1948-1971 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - Receipts, Gilding Work, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Receipts, Art Supplies, 1954-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
  - Receipts, Sale of Station Wagon, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Receipts, Travel, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Receipts, Miscellaneous, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Estate File, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
- Writings, 1955-1988; Series 4; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 5
  Writings include Fitzgerald's notebook, his notes on gilding and various topics, an essay about the ship, "The Elizabeth Howard," an essay by an unidentified author about Fitzgerald's and Rockwell Kent's friendship, and essays on Fitzgerald. Also in the series are index cards containing notes for a catalog of the 1984 exhibition, "James Fitzgerald," by Calvin Hennig. There are also interviews and accompanying transcripts that relate friends' recollections of Fitzgerald. Recordings are on 4 sound cassettes.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  4.1: By Fitzgerald, 1955-1971
  4.2: By Others, 1960-1988
  - By Fitzgerald, 1960; 4.1
    - Manuscript, "Elizabeth Howard", circa 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Notebook, Fitzgerald, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Notes, Business Cards, circa 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Notes, On Gilding, circa 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1971 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - By Others, 1960; 4.2
    - Essay, "James Fitzgerald," by Anne Hubert, circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Essay, On the Friendship Between Fitzgerald and Rockwell Kent, by Anne Hubert, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Essay, "James Fitzgerald," by Elisabeth Levi de Montezinos, circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Essay, "Recollections of James Fitzgerald," by Marjorie Lloyd, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Essay, "James Fitzgerald," by Dorothy Walter, circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Essay, "James Fitzgerald and Mt. Katahdin," Author Unknown, circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Gallery Talk, "Recollections of the Artist James Fitzgerald," by Anne Hubert, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Interview, Don Cundy on Fitzgerald, 1980; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Interview, Sandra Dickson and Harry Bone on Fitzgerald, 1987; 2 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Interview, Jennifer Phillips on Fitzgerald, 1983; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Interview Transcript, Doris Young on Fitzgerald, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Notes, Fitzgerald Biography, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Notes, Fitzgerald Biography, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
    - Notes, Fitzgerald Biography, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11-15)
    - Notes, Fitzgerald Biography, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 16-19)
      Notes by Calvin Hennig.
    - Gallery Proof, James Fitzgerald Catalog, William A. Farnsworth Library and Art Museum, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Oversized Gallery Proof from Box 3, Folder 20 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Artwork, 1930-1969; Series 5; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Artwork consists of 14 drawings and 21 sketchbooks dating from 1921-1969. Sketchbooks include renderings of Monhegan seascapes, and travel sketches from Mt. Katahdin, London, and Ireland.
  Materials are arranged by document type; sketchbooks are in numerical order.
  - Drawings, circa 1921-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Oversize material housed in Box 5, Folder 2.
  - Sketchbook #1, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook #2, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook #3, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook #4, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook #5, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook #6, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook #7, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook #8, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook #9, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook #10, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook #11, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook #12, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook #13, circa 1955-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook #14, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook #15, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook #16, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook #17, circa 1960-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook #18, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook #19, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook #20, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook #21, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Drawings from Box 4, Folder 1, circa 1921-1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1923-1989; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  Printed material includes clippings and a clippings scrapbook that includes four letters and a sampling of exhibition catalogs. There are also exhibition announcements and catalogs, reproductions of art work, programs, art supply catalogs, picture postcards, a brochure and geological survey maps of Mt. Katahdin, yearbook ARTGUM excerpts, and miscellaneous printed material. A videocassette, "James Fitzgerald: Paintings and Drawings from the Collection of Anne and Edgar Hubert," is narrated by Anne Hubert and produced by Eric Shambroom.
  - Clippings, 1930-1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, Scrapbook, 1928-1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Exhibition, "Paintings and Drawings from the Collection of Anne and Edgar Hubert" at the DeCordova Museum, 1985; 1 videocassettes: VHS (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Postcards, circa 1950-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Programs, 1930-1967 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1960-1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Supply Catalogs, 1929-1949 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Travel Brochures, circa 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Yearbook, "Artgum", 1923 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, Mt. Katahdin, circa 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Photographic Material, 1905-1992; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 4
  Photographs are of Fitzgerald; his parents and siblings; his wife Pegs; friends, including actor Richard Boone, Dan Burne Jones, E. F. Ricketts, and John Steinbeck; his studios, including the Kent-Fitzgerald cottage; travel sights; the hotel in which Fitzgerald died; and objects owned and designed by Fitzgerald. Photographs and slides of artwork include portraits of servicemen drawn in 1947.
  Materials are arranged by subject matter and document type.
  - James Fitzgerald, circa 1905-1933 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - James Fitzgerald, 1960-1968 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - James Fitzgerald with Friends, 1930-1966 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Pegs Fitzgerald, circa 1925-1945 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Kent-Fitzgerald Cottage, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Studios, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Travel, 1967-1979 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1992 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Portraits of Servicemen Drawn in 1947, circa 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Slides of Artwork, Katahdin, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Slides of Artwork, Monhegan, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Slides of Artwork, Western Themes, 1977-1988 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Slides of Artwork, Miscellaneous Themes, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 39)